Freligh Family; Papers mss071
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Freligh Family Papers
1773-1955
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
mss071
0.9 cubic ft.
This collection documents the activities of the members of the Freligh family who lived primarily in the Niskayuna area during the 18th, 19th, and 20th centuries.
Scope and Contents
Includes correspondence of Dr. Michael Freligh (1770-1853) about family matters, agriculture, the War of 1812 in Plattsburgh, New York, and the Watervliet Lyceum, 1799-1853; land transactions and legal documents, 1773-1955; and rent receipts signed by Stephen Van Rensselaer, 1804-1830. The Freligh family resided in Niskayuna; Watervliet; and Cohoes, New York.
Biographical Sketch
Members of the Freligh family lived in the Niskayuna area during the 18th, 19th, and 20th centuries. George J. Freligh was born ca. 1750 and died in 1800. Dr. Michael Freligh, the son of George J. Freligh of Dutchess County, N.Y., was born in 1770. He settled in Niskayuna in 1788. Freligh served as Albany County coroner, and in 1815 he was elected to the Assembly of the City and County of Albany. He died in 1853. Michael's brother John Freligh settled in Plattsburgh, N.Y., where he witnessed the burning of Plattsburgh during the War of 1812. His first wife Betsy died in 1811, but by 1814 he had remarried a woman named Margaret. The dates of his birth and death are unknown. George W. Freligh, the son of Dr. Michael Freligh, considered seeking his fortune in California, but ultimately remained in Niskayuna on property inherited from his father. George died in 1881. Abram Freligh, the son of George W. Freligh, served as commissioner of highways for the Town of Colonie. He died in 1912. His daughter, Julia Fort Freligh, married Abram Rand. She died in 1959.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Acquisition Information
The Freligh Family Papers were donated to the University Libraries by the executor of the estate of Julia Fort Freligh Rand, ca. 1965.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Albany, New York; Land trusts.; Deeds.; New York (State)--History--War of 1812
- Land Indentures of George Jury Freligh (Charlotte and Rhinebeck Precincts - Dutchess Co), 1773-1784 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Land Indentures of George Jury Freligh (Charlotte and Rhinebeck Precincts - Dutchess Co), 1773-1784 (Oversized 1, Flat-file 1)
- Bills and Receipts: Dr. Michael Freligh (Expenses of Everyday Living), 1783-1812 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence of Dr. Michael Freligh, 1787-1815 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence of Dr. Michael Freligh, 1787-1815 (Oversized 1, Flat-file 2)
- Ephemera of Dr. Michael Freligh and Julia (Fort) Freligh (Mrs. Abram) Rand, 1787-1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Land Indentures of Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh - Rent and Taxes Paid, 1793-1809 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Land Indentures of Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh - Rent and Taxes Paid, 1793-1809 (Oversized 1, Flat-file 3)
- Bills and Receipts: Dr. Michael Freligh (Expenses of Everyday Living), 1800-1812 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Land Indentures of Dr. Michael Freligh and Anna Whitbeck Freligh - Taxes Paid, 1810-1832; 1856; 1858-1862 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Land Indentures of Dr. Michael Freligh and Anna Whitbeck Freligh - Taxes Paid, 1810-1832; 1856; 1858-1862 (Oversized 1, Flat-file 4)
- Land Indentures of Dr. Michael Freligh and Anna Whitbeck Freligh - Taxes Paid, 1810-1832; 1856; 1858-1862 (Flat-file 1)
- Land Indentures of Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh - Rent and Taxes Paid, 1811-1855 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Land Indentures of Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh - Rent and Taxes Paid, 1811-1835 (Oversized 1, Flat-file 5)
- Bills and Receipts: Dr. Michael Freligh (Expenses of Everyday Living), 1813-1825 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence of Dr. Michael Freligh, 1816-1853 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence of Dr. Michael Freligh, 1816-1853 (Oversized 1, Flat-file 6)
- Bills and Receipts: Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh (Brother) - (Expenses of Everyday Living), 1826-1829 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Bills and Receipts: Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh - (Expenses of Everyday Living), 1830-1833 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Bills and Receipts: Dr. Michael Freligh, John B. and George Freligh (Brothers), 1831-1832 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Bills and Receipts: Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh - (Expenses of Everyday Living), 1834-1835 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Land Indentures of Dr. Michael Freligh, Abram Freligh, and W.H. Freligh, 1835; 1846; 1886 (Oversized 1, Flat-file 7)
- Map - Town of Knox Wood Lots, 1835 (Flat-file 2)
- Land Indentures of Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh - Rent and Taxes Paid, 1836-1854 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Land Indentures of Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh - Rent and Taxes Paid, 1836-1854 (Oversized 1, Flat-file 8)
- Bills and Receipts: Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh - (Expenses of Everyday Living), 1836-1839 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Bills and Receipts: Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh - (Expenses of Everyday Living), 1840-1859 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Land Indentures of Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh - Rent and Taxes Paid Insurance Policies, 1856-1889 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Land Indentures of Dr. Michael Freligh and George Freligh - Rent and Taxes Paid Insurance Policies, 1856-1889 (Oversized 1, Flat-file 9)
- Bills and Receipts: George Freligh and Abram W. Freligh, 1860-1895 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Estate Settlement of George Freligh, 1881-1889 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Abram W. Freligh - Land Indentures-Rent Receipt Stock Payment, 1882-1909 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Tax Receipts of Abram W. and Julia (Fort) Freligh Rand, 1896-1920 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Bills and Receipts - Miss Julia (Fort) Freligh (Mrs. Abram) Rand, 1900-1929 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Abram W. Freligh - Acts as Commissioner of Highways - Town of Colonie with Schenectady Railroad Co. (Street Surface Railroad), 1901-1902 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Estate of Abram W. Freligh - Insurance Policies (Also Living Residence of Julia Fort Freligh Rand), 1911-1936 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Estate of Abram W. Freligh - Insurance Policies (Also Living Residence of Julia Fort Freligh Rand), 1911-1936 (Flat-file 3)
- Estate Settlement of Abram W. Freligh, 1911-1915 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Correspondence of Mrs. Julia Freligh (Widow of Abram Freligh) from T.J. Wallace and Son, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Land Indentures of Julia A. (Fort) Freligh Rand (Includes Death Certificate of JF.F. Rand), 1913-1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Bills and Receipts - Mrs. Julia (Fort)Freligh (Mrs. Abram) Rand, 1930-1943 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Tax Receipts of Abram W. and Julia (Fort) Freligh Rand (Estate), 1921-1955 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Ephemera: Tintype, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)